Finding Aid for Norse Civic Association records, 1934-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Norse Civic Association records 1934-2007
Norse Civic Association.
852017 Bd 2
Detroit area Scandinavian-American civic organization; organizational records; files relating to Scandinavian-American history, organizations, and personages.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the organization (donor no. 4826 ).
The record group is open to research.
On April 4, 1934, a group of metropolitan Detroit Scandinavians came together with the purpose of establishing an organization that would "create a better understanding of unity, cooperation, and of the high ideals of the Scandinavian Races." Subsequently, an organizational meeting was held where articles of incorporation were signed and a slate of officers selected.
The purpose of the organization was to bring together individuals of Scandinavian birth, to instruct them "in the duties and privileges of citizenship" and to carry out plans and programs of a civic character for the betterment of the state of Michigan. During the depression, the Association gave aid to needy families and helped fellow Scandinavians find employment. And throughout its history, the organization sought to commemorate Scandinavian customs and history. These events included the observance of the traditional Midsummer Festival and the designation of October 9 as Leif Erikson Day. In 1939, the organization began publishing a newsletter and in 1963, approved an amendment to its articles of incorporation granting scholarships to students of Nordic descent.
The organization disbanded in 2006.
The Norse Civic Association records consist of organizational records and files relating to Scandinavian-American history, organizations, and personages. The records have been divided into the following series: Organizational materials; Correspondence and other papers; Minutes; Other records; Collected historical materials; and Research files of Christian Feddersen on Scandinavians in Michigan.
Subjects:
Danish Americans--Michigan.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Finnish Americans--Michigan.; Leif Erikson Memorial Association.; Norse Civic Association.; Scandinavian Americans--Michigan.; Scandinavia--Emigration and immigration.; Immigrants--Michigan.; Immigrants--Michigan--Societies, etc.
Contributors:
Feddersen, Christian T.
- Organizational materials
  - Constitution and articles of incorporation (Box 1)
  - Lists of officers (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other papers
  (most files arranged by year, then alphabetically)
  - 1934-1941, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - 1942-1956 1970-1972, 8 folders (Box 2)
- Minutes and related materials
  - 1934-1989, 22 folders (Box 2)
- Other records
  - Combined record book 1969-1982: include meeting agenda, treasurer's records, president's reports, scholarship information, etc. (Box 6)
  - Reports to Michigan Corporation and Securities Commission, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Dissolution of the organization 2006-2007 (Box 6)
  - Financial reports 1983-2004 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's reports 1975-1981 (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Membership material, 4 volumes; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Membership card file, 2 boxes (Box 3)
  - American Scandinavian Foundation, Detroit Chapter (Box 3)
  - Scandinavian Central Coordinating Committee (Box 3)
  - Danish Memorial Garden Fund, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Leif Erikson Memorial Association, 5 folders (Box 3)
- Collected historical materials
  - Letters from Denmark to Michigan (?) circa 1900 (Box 3)
    (in Danish)
  - World War I letters of Hyland Flint of Chicago, Ill. 1917-1918 (Box 3)
- Research files of Christian Feddersen on Scandinavians in Michigan
  - Ackerman, Helmer (Box 4)
  - American-Swedish Club (Box 4)
  - American Union of Swedish Singers (Box 4)
  - Apostolic Lutheran Church (Box 4)
  - Arpi Swedish Male Chorus (Box 4)
  - Augustana Evangelical Lutheran Church (Box 4)
  - Berglund, Carl (Box 4)
  - Bethlehem Lutheran Church (Box 4)
  - Birkelo, Carl C. (Box 4)
  - Caswell, William Henry (Box 4)
  - Dahlberg, LeRoy W. (Box 4)
  - Dahlen, Gustav (Box 4)
  - Danish Ambassador (Box 4)
  - Danish Brotherhood in America (Box 4)
  - Danish Festival, Greenville, Mich. 1968 (Box 4)
  - Danish Festival, Greenville, Mich. 1969 (Box 4)
  - Danish Information office (Box 4)
  - Danish Sisterhood of America (Box 4)
  - Detroit-Swedish Council, Inc. (Box 4)
  - Ehrling, Sixten (Box 4)
  - Eriksen, Edward L. (Box 4)
  - Everson, George P. (Box 4)
  - Finnish Ambassador (Box 4)
  - Reflections of Finland (Box 4)
  - Finlandia Male chorus of Detroit (Box 4)
  - Gellein, Hilmer (Box 4)
  - Grotell, Maija (Box 4)
  - Hofstad, Lawrence R. (Box 4)
  - Hansen, Fred A. (Box 4)
  - Headbloom, Gustav (Box 4)
  - Reflections of Iceland (Box 4)
  - Iceland (Box 4)
  - Iceland (History of Music) (Box 4)
  - Icelandic Ambassador (Box 4)
  - Immanuel Lutheran Church (Box 4)
  - Jacobson, Arvid W. (Box 4)
  - Jenny Lind Club of Detroit (Box 4)
  - Johansson, Carl Edvard (Box 4)
  - Johansson, Edward (Box 4)
  - Jones, Ernest A. (Box 4)
  - Knights and Ladies of Kaleva (Box 4)
  - Kline, Svea (Box 4)
  - Knudsen, Semon E. (Box 4)
  - Knudsen, William S. (Box 4)
  - Koebel Diamond Tool Co. (Box 4)
  - Larsson, B.H. (Box 5)
  - Leif Erikson Association (Box 5)
  - Lindquist, Lilly (Box 5)
  - Lundin, Oscar A. (Box 5)
  - Markstrum, John A. (Box 5)
  - Martinson, Martin H. (Box 5)
  - Milles, Carl (Box 5)
  - Norse Civic Association (Box 5)
  - Norse Civic Association-25th & 30th Anniversaries (Box 5)
  - Northwest Emmanuel Lutheran Church (Box 5)
  - Norwegian Festival Orchestra (Box 5)
  - Ombudsman (Box 5)
  - Oxford, Carl J. (Box 5)
  - Parsons, Carl B. (Box 5)
  - Quarnstrom, Ivar T (Box 5)
  - Order of Runeberg (Box 5)
  - Ryding, Reuben (Box 5)
  - St. Johnts Lutheran Church (Detroit) (Box 5)
  - St. Olaf Evangelical Lutheran Church (Detroit) (Box 5)
  - St. Peter's Danish Lutheran Church (Detroit) (Box 5)
  - Saarinen family (Box 5)
  - Salvation Army (Box 5)
  - Scandinavian Airlines Male Chorus (Box 5)
  - Scandinavian Symphony Orchestra (Box 5)
  - Scandinavian Symphony Society (Box 5)
  - Seaborg, Glenn T. (Box 5)
  - Simonsen, Fred A. (Box 5)
  - Sippola, George W. (Box 5)
  - Sons of Norway (Box 5)
  - Stockholm Restaurant (Box 5)
  - Strohm, Adam (Box 5)
  - Suomi College (Box 5)
  - Swedish Engineers' Society (Box 5)
  - Vasa Lodges of America (Box 5)
  - Virjo, Harri M. (Box 5)
  - Wade, Harry V. (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea (Box 5)
  - Clippings (Box 5)